Chapter 72.
The monkey rope.
In the tumultuous business of cutting in and attending to a whale, there is much
running backwards and forwards among the crew. Now hands are wanted here, and
then again hands are wanted there. There is no staying in any one place, for at
one in the same time everything has to be done everywhere. It is much the same
with him who endeavors the description of the scene. We must now retrace our
way a little. It was mentioned that upon first breaking ground in the whale's
back, the blubber hook was inserted into the original hole there cut by the
spades of the mates. But how did so clumsy and weighty a mass as that same
hook get fixed in that hole? It was inserted there by my particular friend
Quiqu whose duty it was as harpooner to descend upon the monster's back for the
special purpose referred to. But in very many cases circumstances require that
the harpooner shall remain on the whale till the whole tensing or stripping
operation is concluded. The whale be it observed lies almost entirely submerged
excepting the immediate parts operated upon. So down there, some 10 ft below
the level of the deck, the poor harpooner flounders about, half on the
whale and half in the water, as the vast mass revolves like a treadmill beneath
him. On the occasion in question, Quiqu figured in the Highland costume, a shirt
and socks, in which, to my eyes at least, he appeared to uncommon
advantage, and no one had a better chance to observe him, as will presently be seen.
Being the savage's bowsman, that is the person who pulled the bow ore in his
boat, the second one from forward, it was my cheerful duty to attend upon him
while taking that hard scrabble scramble upon the dead whale's back. You have
seen Italian organ boys holding a dancing ape by a long cord. Just so from
the ship's steep side did I hold Quiquake down there in the sea by what
is technically called in the fishery a monkey rope attached to a strong strip
of canvas belted round his waist. It was a humorously perilous business for both
of us. For before we proceed further, it must be said that the monkey rope was
fast at both ends, fast to Que's broad canvas belt and fast to my narrow
leather one. So that for better or for worse we too for the time were wedded.
And should poor Quiquake sink to rise no more, then both usage and honor demanded
that instead of cutting the cord it should drag me down in his wake. So then
an elongated Siamese ligature united us.
Quiqu was my own inseparable twin brother. Nor could I any way get rid of
the dangerous liabilities which the hemp and bond entailed.
So strongly and metaphysically did I conceive of my situation then that while
earnestly watching his motions, I seemed distinctly to perceive that my own
individuality was now merged in a joint stock company of two, that my free will
had received a mortal wound, and that another's mistake or misfortune might
plunge innocent me into unmmerited disaster and death. Therefore, I saw
that here was a sort of interregnum in providence, for its even-handed equity
never could have so gross an injustice.
And yet, still further pondering, while I jerked him now and then from between
the whale and the ship, which would threaten to jam him, still further
pondering, I say, I saw that this situation of mind was the precise
situation of every mortal that breathes.
only in most cases he one way or other has this Siamese connection with a
plurality of other mortals. If your banker breaks, you snap. If your
apothecary by mistake sends you poison in your pills, you die. True, you may
say that by exceeding caution, you may possibly escape these and multitudinous
other evil chances of life. But handle Que's monkey rope heedfully as I would.
Sometimes he jerked it so that I came very near sliding overboard. Nor could I
possibly forget that do what I would, I had only the management of one end of
it. Footnote. The monkey rope is found in all whalers, but it was only in the
peekquad that the monkey and his holder were ever tied together. This
improvement upon the original usage was introduced by no less a man than stub in
order to afford the imperiled harpineer the strongest possible guarantee for the
faithfulness and vigilance of his monkey rope holder. End a footnote.
I have hinted that I would often jerk poor Quiquake from between the whale and
the ship, where he would occasionally fall from the incessant rolling and
swaying of both. But this was not the only jamming jeopardy he was exposed to.
Unappalled by the massacre made upon them during the night, the sharks, now
freshly and more keenly allured by the before pent blood which began to flow
from the carcass, the rabid creatures swarmed round it like bees in a beehive.
And right in among those sharks was Queiqu, who often pushed them aside with
his floundering feet, a thing altogether incredible, were it not that attracted
by such prey as a dead whale, the otherwise miscellaneous carnivorous
sharks will seldom touch a man.
Nevertheless, it may well be believed that since they have such a ravenous
finger in the pie, it is deemed but wise to look sharp to them. Accordingly,
besides the monkey rope, with which I now and then jerked the poor fellow from
too close of vicinity to the maw of what seemed a peculiarly ferocious shark, he
was provided with still another protection. Suspended over the side in
one of the stages, Tashego and Dagu continually flourished over his head a
couple of keen whale spades, wherewith they slaughtered as many sharks as they
could reach. This procedure of theirs, to be sure, was very disinterested and
benevolent of them. They meant Quiquake's best happiness, I admit, but
in their hasty zeal to befriend him, and from the circumstance that both he and
the sharks were at times half hidden by the blood muddled water, those
indiscrete spades of theirs would come nearer amputating a leg than a tail. But
poor Quiquake, I suppose, straining and gasping there with that great iron hook.
Poor Quiquake, I suppose, only prayed to his yojo, and gave up his life into the
hands of his gods.
"Well, well, my dear comrade and twin brother," thought I, as I drew in, and
then slacked off the rope to every swell of the sea. What matters it, after all?
Are you not the precious image of each and all of us men in this whailing
world? That unsounded ocean you gasp in is life. Those sharks your foes, those
spades your friends. And what between sharks and spades you are in a sad
pickle in peril, poor lad. But courage, there is good cheer in store for you,
Quiquake. For now, as with blue lips and bloodshot eyes, the exhausted savage at
last climbs up the chains, and stands all dripping and involuntarily trembling
over the side, the steward advances, and with a benevolent, consolatory glance,
hands him what? Some hot cognac? No.
Hands him, ye God, hands him a cup of tepid ginger and water.
Ginger? Do I smell ginger? suspiciously asked stub coming near. "Yes, this must
be ginger." Peering into the as yet untasted cup, then standing as if
incredulous for a while, he calmly walked toward the astonished steward,
slowly saying, "Ginger, ginger. And will you have the goodness to tell me, Mr.
Doughboy, where lies the virtue of ginger? Ginger? Is ginger the sort of
fuel you use, doughboy, to kindle a fire in this shivering cannibal? Ginger? What
the devil is ginger? Sea coal, firewood, Lucifer matches, tinder, gunpowder. What
the devil is ginger? I say that you offer this cup to our poor Quag here.
There is some sneaking temperance society movement about this business, he
suddenly added, now approaching Starbucks, who had just come from
forward. Will you look at that, sir?
Smell of it if you please. Then, watching the mate's countenance, he
added, "The steward, Mr. Starbucks, had the face to offer that calam and jallop
to Quiquake there this instant off the whale. Is the steward an apothecary,
sir? And may I ask whether this is the sort of bitters by which he blows back
the life into a half-drowned man.
I trust not, said Starbucks. It is poor stuff enough. I I steward cried Stub.
We'll teach you to drug it, Harpaneer.
None of your apothecaries medicine here.
You want to poison us, do you? You have got out insurance on our lives and want
to murder us all and pocket the proceeds, do you?
It was not me, cried Doughboy. It was Aunt Charity that brought the ginger on
board, and Badme never give the harpooners any spirits, but only this
ginger jub, so she called it. Ginger Job, you gingery rascal. Take that and
run along with you to the lockers and get something better. I hope I do no
wrong, Mr. Starbucks. It is the captain's orders. Grog for the harpooner
on a whale. Enough, replied Starbucks.
only don't hit him again. But oh, I never hurt when I hit except when I hit
a whale or something of that sort, and this fellow's a weasel. What were you
about saying, sir? Only this. Go down with him, and get what thou wantest thyself.
When Stub reappeared, he came with a dark flask in one hand, and a sort of
tea caddy in the other. The first contained strong spirits, and was handed
to Quiqu. The second was Aunt Charity's gift, and that was freely given to the waves.